Guide to the John Rutherfurd Papers 1726-1835 (bulk 1775-1835) MS 533
New-York Historical Society
John Rutherfurd Papers
1726-1835 (bulk 1775-1835)
New-York Historical Society
MS 533
2.5 Linear feet (5 boxes)
The John Rutherfurd Papers is one of four discrete but closely related collections, known together as the Alexander - Stuyvesant - Rutherfurd Collections. The John Rutherfurd Papers consist principally of material relating to or created by John Rutherfurd (1760 - 1840), and his father, Walter Rutherfurd (1724 - 1804). Principal subseries for John and Walter Rutherfurd are Correspondence; Accounts, Bills, Receipts; Legal Papers; and Court Papers. Correspondence includes letters to John or Walter Rutherfurd, and drafts of their replies.
Provenance
Donation, Lewis Morris Rutherfurd, 1884
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Biographical Note for the Alexander - Stuyvesant - Rutherfurd Collections
Missing Title
1691 James Alexander born in Scotland, May 27
1693 Mary Spratt born in New York, April 17
1711 Mary Spratt marries Samuel Provoost, October 15
1715 James Alexander arrives in New York
[1719] Samuel Provoost dies
1721 Mary Spratt Provoost marries James Alexander, June 5
1721 Mary Alexander II born
1722 Susanna Alexander born
1726 William Alexander born
1729 Catherine Alexander born
17?? Elizabeth Alexander born
17?? Walter Rutherfurd born in [Edgerston, Roxburghshire] Scotland
1739 Mary Alexander II marries Peter Van Brugh Livingston
1748 William Alexander marries Sarah Livingston
17?? Elizabeth Alexander marries John Stevens
1756 James Alexander dies
1756 Walter Rutherfurd arrives in America. Serves in the Royal American Regiment
1758 Catherine Alexander marries Walter Rutherfurd
1760 Mary Alexander dies, April 18
1760 John Rutherfurd born September 20
1767 Mary Alexander Livingston dies
1782 John Rutherfurd marries Helena Morris October 30. Walter Rutherfurd presents John Rutherfurd with Tranquillity (sic) estate in Allamuchy, Warren County, New Jersey
1783 William Alexander dies, January 15
1788 Robert Walter Rutherfurd born in May
1800 Elizabeth Alexander Stevens dies
1801 Catherine Alexander Rutherfurd dies
1804 Walter Rutherfurd dies January 10
1807 Gen. John Reid dies February 6, at the age of 86
1808 John Rutherfurd moves to Edgerston on the Passaic River
1809 Robert Walter Rutherfurd marries Sabina Morris
1809 Helena Rutherfurd marries Peter Gerard Stuyvesant
1816 Lewis Morris Rutherfurd born November 25 to Robert Walter Rutherfurd and Sabina Morris Rutherfurd
1841 Lewis Morris Rutherfurd marries Margaret Chanler July 22
1842 Stuyvesant Rutherfurd born to Lewis Morris Rutherfurd and Margaret Chanler Rutherfurd
1847 Peter Gerard Stuyvesant dies August 16
[1847] In accordance with a provision of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant's will, Stuyvesant Rutherfurd changes his name to Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
1854 Margaret Rutherfurd born
1859 Louisa Morris Rutherfurd born March 31
ca. 1860 Lewis Morris Rutherfurd Jr. born
1862 Winthrop Rutherfurd born
1863 Rutherfurd Stuyvesant marries Mary Pierrepont
1870 Robert Walter Rutherfurd dies
1873 Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant dies
1879 Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant dies
1879 Margaret Rutherfurd marries Henry White, December 3
1892 Louisa M. Rutherfurd dies
1902 Rutherfurd Stuyvesant marries Countess Matilde E. de Wassanaer (nee Matilde Lowenguth), June 16
1903 Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant born
1906 Alain Stuyvesant born
1907 Stuyvesant Rutherfurd dies July 4
1916 Margaret Rutherfurd White dies
1925 Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant marries Rosalie Pillot
1927 Henry White dies at the age of 77
19?? Lewis Morris Rutherfurd Jr. dies
1944 Winthrop Rutherfurd dies
1944 Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant dies, September 7
1948 Matilde Lowenguth Stuyvesant (in 1948, Princess Alexandre de Caraman Chimay) dies, July 10
1954 Alain Stuyvesant dies, Februrary 9
For more information on some of the persons represented in these collections consult:
Biographical Dictionaries
Dictionary of American Biography- James and William Alexander, Lewis Morris Rutherfurd
American National Biography- James, Mary, and William Alexander, Lewis Morris Rutherfurd, Henry White
Dictionary of National Biography- John Reid
Books
Rutherfurd, Livingston Family Records and Events New York, De Vinne Press, 1894
Valentine, Alan Chester Lord Stirling New York, Oxford University Press, 1969
Scope and Content Notes
Scope and Content for the Alexander - Stuyvesant - Rutherfurd Collections
The John Rutherfurd Papers is one of four discrete but closely related collections. The largest and the smallest of the four collections, the Alexander Papers and the John Rutherfurd Papers, were originally a single donation, made in the late 19th Century. The remaining two collections, the Rutherfurd Family Papers and the Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers, were donated separately in the 1970's.
Together, these collections chronicle seven generations of an extended family in New York an d New Jersey over the course of two centuries. The founders of the family were James and Mary Alexander, who married in 1721. James Alexander had merchant business, but was primarily active as an attorney and government official in New York and New Jersey. Most of the material in the Alexander Papers derives from James Alexander's legal practice in both colonies, and from his tenures as Surveyor General of New Jersey, and Attorney General of New York. Other material in the Alexander Papers documents Mary Alexander's merchant business in New York, and the business activities and pre-Revolutionary military service of their son, William Alexander (Lord Stirling).
While the daughters of James and Mary Alexander are underrepresented in these collections, their husbands are represented to a greater or lesser extent in each of the collections described below. The Alexanders' four daughters married men who were or would become leading figures in New York and New Jersey. Mary married Peter Van Brugh Livingston, Susanna married John Reid, and Elizabeth married John Stevens. Catherine Alexander married Walter Rutherfurd.
The marriage of Catherine and Walter Rutherfurd also produced a son, John Rutherfurd, who evidently inherited the bulk of his father's and grandfather's papers. In 1847, Stuyvesant Rutherfurd (a grandson John Rutherfurd and nephew of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant), changed his name to Rutherfurd Stuyvesant in accordance with a provision of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant's will. Rutherfurd Stuyvesant evidently inherited at least some of the papers of his uncle. The Rutherfurd collections contain material created by or pertaining to the Alexander family, and the Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers contain material created by or pertaining to the Alexanders and the Stuyvesants.
The material the Rutherfurd collections relates primarily to the landholdings and business undertakings of a wealthy and socially prominent family. The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers documents the activities of later generations of that family. By the mid-nineteenth century, the family had become more occupied in strictly leisure activities.
Various descendants of John Rutherfurd donated the collections described in these finding aids to the New-York Historical Society, and the collections extensively document the business dealings, professional activities, and family relationships of the Alexanders during the 18th Century, and the Rutherfurds from the 18th until the early 20th centuries.
For finding aids to the other three collections, click on the following links:
The Alexander Papers
The Rutherfurd Family Papers
The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers
Scope and Content for the John Rutherfurd Papers
This collection consists principally of material relating to or created by John Rutherfurd (1760 - 1840), and his father, Walter Rutherfurd (1724 - 1804). The inclusive dates of the collection are 1775 - 1835. The collection also contains small amounts of business-related material concerning persons who were associated with or related to John and Walter Rutherfurd. These include John Duncan, Alexander Hamilton, Gen. John Reid, and Alexander McDonald. Two institutions with which John Rutherfurd was affiliated, the Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures, and the Corporation for the Relief of Widows and Children of Clergymen of the Episcopal Church, are also represented in the collection.
Principal subseries for John and Walter Rutherfurd are Correspondence; Accounts, Bills, Receipts; Legal Papers; and Court Papers. Correspondence includes letters to John or Walter Rutherfurd, and drafts of their replies. Deeds, agreements, contracts, leases, and other legally binding documents are in the Legal Papers subseries. However, such legally binding documents that are identified as having to do with specific court cases or suits are foldered with the appropriate suit in the Court Papers series. Accounts, Bills, Receipts is self-explanatory.
There is also a series in the collection entitled Other Persons. This series consists of small numbers of items created by or pertaining to persons other than John or Walter Rutherfurd. The subseries in this series include Correspondence; Accounts, Bills, Receipts; Legal Papers; and Court Papers. Certain material relating to some persons is extensive enough to merit those persons being given subseries within this series. Persons with specific subseries within this series are John Duncan (legal papers only), Gen. Alexander Hamilton, Alexander McDonald, and Gen. John Reid. With these exceptions, material for all other persons is interfiled according to format, in chronological order.
Material pertaining to John Rutherfurd consists primarily of business correspondence and legal papers such as deeds, conveyances, and leases. Some material reflects his interest in the development infrastructure, such as roads and bridges, in New Jersey. There is very little family material of any kind in the collection. None of the material concerns John Rutherfurd's political career or political affairs. Most of the material pertaining to Walter Rutherfurd is also business-related.
Arrangement
The John Rutherfurd Papers are organized into the following eight series:
Missing Title
Series I: John Rutherfurd
Series II: Walter Rutherfurd
Series III: Other Persons
Series IV: Corporation for the Relief of Widows and Children of CLergymen
Series V: Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures
Series VI: Abstracts of Legislation re New Jersey -- New York Boundary
Series VII: [Map of Turnpike Route]
Series VIII: Fragments
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The Alexander Papers
The Rutherfurd Family Papers
The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers
Alexander Papers - Account Books Relating to the Equivalent Lands
Alexander, James - Journal 1718 - 1769
Alexander, James - Records and Accounts Relating to his Services in Behalf of the Children of Governors Burnet and Hunter, 1718 - 1745
Alexander, James - Register of Cases, New York Supreme Court, 1721 - 1742
Alexander, William - Ledger, 1766 - 1775
Alexander, William - Account Books, 1756 - 1758, 1763 - 1777
Alexander, William - Battoeman's Book, 1756
Alexander, William - Papers Relating to the Disposition of Lord Stirling's lands in Nova Scotia, 1831 - 1838, plus Copies of Earlier Papers
Alexander, William - [Material concerning the legality of William Alexander's Claim to the Title of earl of Stirling] compiled ca. 1857
Alexander - Livingston - Moore Account Book, ca. 1774 - 1785
William Alexander Papers
Rutherfurd Collection
Lord Stirling Papers
Powers of attorney; Accounts.; Agriculture -- New Jersey.; Sheep; Wool; Bridges -- Design and construction -- New Jersey.; Roads -- Design and construction -- New Jersey.; New Jersey -- Boundaries -- New York (State); Chenango County (N.Y.); New York (State) -- Boundaries -- New Jersey.; Legal documents.; Correspondence.; Deeds.; Real property -- New Jersey.; Drawings (visual works); Maps.; Agriculture -- New York (State).; Surveys.; Field notes.; Leases.; Real property -- New York (State); Ernst, John Frederick, -1805; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 -- Estate; McDonald, Alexander, active 1775-1779; Reid, John, 1721-1807 -- Estate; Rutherfurd, Walter, 1723-1804; Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures; Corporation for the Relief of Widows and Children of Clergymen of the Protestant Episcopal Church in the State of New Jersey; Duncan, John, 1727 or 1728-1794
- Series I: John Rutherfurd
  - Subseries 1: John Rutherfurd - Correspondence N.D., 1776 - 1835
    Scope and Contents note
    This subseries consists of letters received by John Rutherfurd, and responses drafted by him or on his behalf. The subseries is arranged chronologically.
    For the most part, the letters concern John Rutherfurd's landholdings in New York and New Jersey. Specific matters relating to John Rutherfurd's landholdings include tenants, sale and lease of lands, collection of rents, and legal matters relating to land titles. Other general subjects include the raising of sheep and the quality of wool, and proposals for the construction of roads and bridges in New Jersey, particularly the Paterson - Hamburg Turnpike.
    There are very few items in the collection that would indicate that a given correspondent wrote frequently to John Rutherfurd. John and Richard Duncan occasionally wrote to John Rutherfurd regarding a debt owed by John Duncan to Rutherfurd and others, and other creditors of Duncan sometimes wrote to Rutherfurd. Several letters of Robert Boggs address the sale of sheep's wool, Elias van Arsdale wrote periodically on legal matters, and Margaret White wrote about legal and business matters that John Rutherfurd managed for her family. In several letters dated 1786, the Rev. John Frederick Ernst inquired about an advertisement for settlers in the Chenango Tract, offering his congregation as candidates. Another cluster of letters, from 1827, consists of several letters that Eliza M. Evans wrote to John Rutherfurd concerning a land dispute between Rutherfurd and her family.
    Also in the series are drafts of letters sent to various persons, including Rev. Ernst, Mrs. Evans (presumably Eliza M. Evans), and Richard Duncan. Other subjects in the drafts include the estate of Gen. John Reid, and his shares in the Delaware & Raritan Canal.
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Letters Received, N.D.; 1776; 1783-1788 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Letters Received, 1789-1802 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Letters Received, 1803-1809 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Letters Received, 1810-1815 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Letters Received, 1816-1819 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Letters Received, 1820-1835 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Drafts of Letters Sent -- A - J, N.D., 1791 - 1835 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Drafts of Letters Sent -- K - Z, N.D., 1791 - 1835 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Drafts of Letters Sent -- Recipients Unknown, N.D.; 1784-1819 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Retained Copies of Letters Sent -- Multiple Recipients, 1822, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Correspondence - - Letter to "Commercial Advertiser" re Turnpikes, [January] 1806 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2: John Rutherfurd - Accounts, Bills, Receipts N.D., 1763 - 1828
    Most items are receipts for rents, milling of wheat, interest on bonds or debts, and taxes.
    - John Rutherfurd -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, N.D.; 1763; 1764; 1784-1800 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1801-1828 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Calculations of Interest on Bonds, 1770 - 1804 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Calculations of Interest on John Duncan's Bond, 1769 - 1804 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 3: John Rutherfurd - Legal Papers 1785 - 1835
    Material includes bonds of the Heirs of Peter Augustus Jay, William and James Jauncey; deeds for lands in New Jersey, primarily Sussex County; and powers of attorney from persons living outside the United States.
    - John Rutherfurd -- Legal Papers -- Bonds, 1785 - 1800 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Legal Papers -- Deeds, 1788-1798; 1804; 1835 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Legal Papers -- Agreements, 1780; 1785-1797 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Legal Papers -- Agreements, 1798-1835 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 4: John Rutherfurd - Court Papers N.D., 1827
    The material consists of an abstract of title from the suit of John Rutherfurd vs. [ ] Shotwell et al., undated; and a bill of costs and a warrant John Rutherfurd vs. Mary Ellis et al., dated 1827.
    - John Rutherfurd -- Court Papers, N.D., 1827 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 5: John Rutherfurd - Delaware River Bridge N.D., 1798, 1802, 1806
    The subseries consists of material having to do with John Rutherfurd's interest in the construction of a bridge linking New Jersey and Pennsylvania. Included are drawings of the proposed bridge, memoranda, calculations, and a report, published in the Trenton Federalist, to the stockholders of the Trenton Delaware Bridge [Company]. The author of the report was John Beatty, who was apparently the president of that company.
    - John Rutherfurd -- Delaware River Bridge -- Drawings, N.D. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Delaware River Bridge -- Calculations, N.D. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Delaware River Bridge/Trenton Ferry -- Memoranda, N.D., 1802 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Delaware River Bridge -- Legislation, N.D., 1798 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Delaware River Bridge -- Report Published in Trenton "Federalist", Feb. 13, 1806 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 6: John Rutherfurd - New Jersey Turnpikes N.D., 1789, 1805, 1806
    This subseries consists of memoranda and copies of legislation regarding the construction of turnpikes in New Jersey.
    - John Rutherfurd -- New Jersey Turnpikes -- Memoranda, N.D., 1789, 1805, 1806 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - John Rutherfurd -- New Jersey Turnpikes -- Legislation, N.D. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 7: John Rutherfurd - Diary Nov. 13-16 1788
    Item is a small, pamphlet-bound volume, with four pages of entries sketching travel in Sussex County, New Jersey, and some calculations.
    - John Rutherfurd -- Diary, Nov. 13-16 1788 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - John Rutherfurd: Other Subseries
    - John Rutherfurd -- Specifications of Baltimore Locomotive Engine, N.D., 1811, 1822, 1829 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Draft of Advertisement for Tenants, N.D. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Draft of Real Estate Advertisements, N.D. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Maps of Cool Spring Farm, N.D., 1824 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Calculations, N.D. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Memoranda, n.D., 1783 - 1833 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - John Rutherfurd -- Samples of Sheep's Wool, N.D. (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Series II: Walter Rutherfurd
  - Subseries 1: Walter Rutherfurd - Correspondence
    This subseries includes letters received by Walter Rutherfurd, and drafts of replies to letters. Most of the material concerns Walter Rutherfurd's land holdings in New Jersey and New York. Specific subjects include surveys, the Business of the Proprietors of the Eastern Division of New Jersey, tenants, and lawsuits. Correspondents include George Reyerse, David Ogden, James Duane, Dirck ten Broeck, and Cornelius Haring.
  - Subseries 2: Walter Rutherfurd - Accounts, Bills, Receipts N.D., 1761 - 1803
    This subseries consists primarily of material having to do with Walter Rutherfurd's land holdings, including lands that he held in common with John Stevens. Some of the accounts detail goods seized from tenants, presumably for nonpayment of rent. Also in the subseries are accounts, apparently prepared annually, of land and interest-bearing bonds held by Walter Rutherfurd.
    - Walter Rutherfurd -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, N.D.; 1761-1803 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Walter Rutherfurd -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts --Annual Accounts of Bonds and Real Estate, 1765 - 1777 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 3: Walter Rutherfurd - Legal Papers N.D.; 1761-1802
    Most of the material in the subseries consist of leases to tenants for farms in New Jersey Earlier material includes powers of attorney from British officers, appointing Walter Rutherfurd to manage their affairs in North America.
  - Subseries 4: Walter Rutherfurd - Court Papers N.D., 1802, 1803
    The subseries contains material from three cases. Material from the case of Walter Rutherfurd vs. Moses Martin Jr., et al. consists of what appears to be a [state of case]. Material from the case of Walter Rutherfurd vs. John Stiles consists of two documents that appear to be warrants. Material from the case of Aaron Ogden & Thomas Gibbons vs. Walter Rutherfurd comprises the bulk of the material in the subseries. Principally, material related to the case consists of the defendant's answers to the charges and counsel's observations on answers to charges.
    - Walter Rutherfurd -- Court Papers, N.D.; 1802, 1803 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 5: Walter Rutherfurd - Memoranda N.D., 1766 - 1795
    This subseries consists primarily of some undated rough calculations of the value of shares, unfinished drafts of legal papers, and lists of crops produced.
    - Walter Rutherfurd -- Memoranda, N.D., 1766 - 1795 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series III: Other Persons
  This series consists of material that does not pertain to John Rutherfurd or Walter Rutherfurd, or pertains to then indirectly. Four specific persons have subseries in the series. These persons are John Duncan, Alexander Hamilton (Estate of -- ), Alexander McDonald, and John Reid. The subseries for John Duncan consists solely of legal papers. Business papers relating to Duncan can be found in the subseries Other Persons - Accounts, Bills, Receipts.
  - Subseries 1: Other Persons - John Duncan N.D., 1766 - 1795
    Subseries consists of legal papers, such as deeds, conveyances, releases, etc. of John Duncan.
    - Other Persons -- John Duncan -- Legal Papers, 1764 - 1785 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Other Persons - Estate of Gen. Alexander Hamilton N.D., 1805
    Subseries consists of legal papers, primarily conveyances, of Gen. Alexander Hamilton, and advertisements for the sale of lands in Scriba's Patent.
    - Other Persons -- Estate of Gen. Alexander Hamilton -- Legal Papers, 1805 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Other Persons -- Estate of Gen. Alexander Hamilton -- Sale of Lands in Scriba's Patent (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 3: Other Persons - Alexander McDonald 1772 - 1786
    Subseries consists of business papers, legal papers and memoranda of Alexander McDonald. The legal papers include a power of attorney authorizing John Rutherfurd to act on McDonald's behalf. The memoranda include lists of deeds and bonds that belonged to McDonald, but were evidently held by John Rutherfurd.
    - Other Persons -- Alexander McDonald - - Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1772 - 1774, 1784, 1786 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Other Persons -- Alexander McDonald - - Legal Papers, 1772, 1773, 1784 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Other Persons -- Alexander McDonald - - Memoranda, N.D., 1784 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 4: Other Persons - General John Reid N.D., 1775 - 1793